And to note the countries that had made a big turnaround: [#ifAfricawasabar Rwanda would be that girl that comes with no money and no transport but leaves drunk, happy and rich] But most importantly, people were using the hashtag to connect. People were connecting over their Africanness.
Y para tomar nota de los países que han hecho un gran cambio: [#ifAfricawasabar Ruanda sería esa chica que viene sin dinero ni transporte, pero se va borracha, feliz y rica]. Pero lo más importante, la gente estaba usando el hashtag para conectarse, para conectarse a través de su africanidad.
So for one week in July, Twitter became a real African bar. And I was really thrilled,
Así que durante una semana en julio, Twitter se convirtió en un auténtico bar africano. Y yo estaba muy emocionada,
mainly because I realized that Pan-Africanism could work, that we had before us, between us, at our fingertips a platform that just needed a small spark
principalmente porque me di cuenta de que el panafricanismo podría funcionar, que teníamos ante nosotros, entre nosotros, en nuestras manos, una plataforma que solo necesitaba una pequeña chispa
to light in us a hunger for each other. My name is Siyanda Mohutsiwa, I'm 22 years old and I am Pan-Africanist by birth. Now, I say I'm Pan-Africanist by birth because my parents are from two different African countries. My father's from a country called Botswana in southern Africa. It's only slightly bigger than Germany. This year we celebrate our 50th year of stable democracy.
para iluminar en nosotros un hambre por el otro. Mi nombre es Siyanda Mohutsiwa, tengo 22 años y soy panafricana de nacimiento. Digo que soy panafricanista de nacimiento porque mis padres son de dos diferentes países africanos. Mi padre de un país llamado Botswana en África meridional. Es solo un poco más grande que Alemania. Este año celebramos nuestro 50 años de democracia estable.
And it has some very progressive social policies. My mother's country is the Kingdom of Swaziland. It's a very, very small country, also in southern Africa. It is Africa's last complete monarchy. So it's been ruled by a king and a royal family in line with their tradition, for a very long time. On paper, these countries seem very different. And when I was a kid, I could see the difference. It rained a lot in one country, it didn't rain quite as much in the other. But outside of that, I didn't really realize why it mattered that my parents were from two different places. But it would go on to have a very peculiar effect on me. You see, I was born in one country and raised in the other. When we moved to Botswana, I was a toddler who spoke fluent SiSwati and nothing else. So I was being introduced to my new home, my new cultural identity, as a complete outsider, incapable of comprehending anything that was being said to me by the family and country whose traditions I was meant to move forward.
Y tiene algunas políticas sociales muy progresistas. El país de mi madre es el Reino de Suazilandia. Es un país pequeñísimo, también en el sur de África. Es la última monarquía absoluta de África. Ha sido gobernado por un rey y una familia real de acuerdo con su tradición, por un largo tiempo. Sobre el papel, estos países parecen ser muy diferentes. Y cuando era una niña, pude ver la diferencia. Llovía mucho en un país, no llovía tanto en el otro. Pero fuera de eso, realmente no me di cuenta de la importancia de que mis padres fueran de dos lugares diferentes. Lo cual tendría un efecto muy peculiar en mí. Verán, yo nací en un país y crecí en el otro. Cuando nos mudamos a Botswana, era una niña que hablaba suazi fluido y nada más. Así que fui introducida a mi nuevo hogar, mi nueva identidad cultural, como una completa extraña, incapaz de comprender nada de lo que se me estaba diciendo por la familia y el país cuyas tradiciones estaba destinada a seguir más adelante.
But very soon, I would shed SiSwati. And when I would go back to Swaziland, I would be constantly confronted by how very non-Swazi I was becoming. Add to that my entry into Africa's private school system, whose entire purpose is to beat the Africanness out of you, and I would have a very peculiar adolescence. But I think that my interest in ideas of identity was born here, in the strange intersection of belonging to two places at once but not really belonging to either one very well and belonging to this vast space in between and around simultaneously. I became obsessed with the idea of a shared African identity. Since then, I have continued to read about politics and geography and identity and what all those things mean. I've also held on to a deep curiosity about African philosophies. When I began to read, I gravitated towards the works of black intellectuals like Steve Biko and Frantz Fanon, who tackled complex ideas like decolonization and black consciousness. And when I thought, at 14, that I had digested these grand ideas, I moved on to the speeches of iconic African statesmen
Pero muy pronto, olvidaría el suazi. Y cuando regresé a Suazilandia, era constantemente confrontada por lo no muy suazi en que me estaba convirtiendo. A eso le sumanos mi entrada al sistema escolar privado de África, cuya propósito último es eliminar la africanidad dentro de uno y tendría una adolescencia muy peculiar. Pero creo que mi interés en las ideas de identidad nació aquí, en la extraña intersección de pertenecer a dos lugares a la vez pero en realidad sin pertenecer a ninguno de los dos muy bien y que pertenecer a este vasto espacio en medio y alrededor al mismo tiempo. Me obsesioné con la idea de una identidad africana compartida. Desde entonces, he seguido leyendo acerca de la política y la geografía y la identidad y lo que significan todas esas cosas. También me he aferrado a una profunda curiosidad por las filosofías africanas. Cuando empecé a leer, gravité hacia las obras de intelectuales negros como Steve Biko y Frantz Fanon, que abordaron ideas complejas como la descolonización y la conciencia negro. Y cuando pensaba que, a los 14 años, había digerido estas grandes ideas, pasé a los discursos de los estadistas africanos icónicos
like Burkina Faso's Thomas Sankara and Congo's Patrice Lumumba. I read every piece of African fiction that I could get my hands on. So when Twitter came, I hopped on with the enthusiasm of a teenage girl whose friends are super, super bored of hearing about all this random stuff. The year was 2011 and all over southern Africa and the whole continent, affordable data packages for smartphones and Internet surfing became much easier to get. So my generation, we were sending messages to each other on this platform that just needed 140 characters and a little bit of creativity. On long commutes to work, in lectures that some of us should have been paying attention to, on our lunch breaks, we would communicate as much as we could
como de Burkina Faso, Thomas Sankara y, de Congo, Patrice Lumumba. Leí cada pieza de ficción africana que pude tener en mis manos. Así que cuando llegó Twitter, salté con el entusiasmo de una adolescente cuyos amigos están de lo más aburridos de oír hablar de todas estas cosas. Era el año 2011 y en todo el sur de África y en todo el continente, se hizo mucho más fácil de conseguir, paquetes asequibles de datos para teléfonos inteligentes y navegación por Internet. Así que mi generación, estaba enviando mensajes entre sí en esta plataforma que solo necesita 140 caracteres y un poco de creatividad. En los largos viajes diarios al trabajo, en las clases en las que algunos deberíamos haber prestando atención, en nuestros almuerzos, queríamos comunicar lo máximo posible
about the everyday realities of being young and African. But of course, this luxury was not available to everybody. So this meant that if you were a teenage girl in Botswana and you wanted to have fun on the Internet, one, you had to tweet in English. Two, you had to follow more than just the three other people you knew online. You had to follow South Africans, Zimbabweans, Ghanaians, Nigerians. And suddenly, your whole world opened up. And my whole world did open up. I followed vibrant Africans who were travelling around the continent, taking pictures of themselves and posting them under the hashtag #myafrica. Because at that time, if you were to search Africa on Twitter or on Google or any kind of social media, you would think that the entire continent was just pictures of animals
sobre las realidades cotidianas de ser joven y africano. Pero, por supuesto, este lujo no estaba disponible para todo el mundo. Así que esto significa que si uno era un adolescente en Botswana y quería divertirse en Internet, tenía que, uno, tuitear en Inglés. Dos, tenías que seguir más de las otras tres personas que conociste en línea. Había que seguir sudafricanos, zimbabuenses, ghaneses, nigerianos. Y de repente, todo su mundo se abrió. Y todo mi mundo sí que se abrió. Seguí a los africanos vibrantes que viajaban por todo el continente, tomando fotografías y colocándolas bajo el hashtag #myafrica. Debido a que en ese momento, si buscaba África en Twitter o en Google o cualquier tipo de medio, se podría pensar que todo el continente era solo imágenes de animales
and white guys drinking cocktails in hotel resorts. (Laughter) But Africans were using this platform to take some kind of ownership of the tourism sectors. It was Africans taking selfies on the beaches of Nigeria. It was Africans in cocktail bars in Nairobi. And these were the same Africans that I began to meet in my own travels around the continent. We would discuss African literature, politics, economic policy.
y chicos blancos bebiendo cócteles en complejos hoteleros. (Risas) Pero los africanos estaban usando esta plataforma para tomar algún tipo de propiedad de los sectores de turismo. Africanos tomando selfis en las playas de Nigeria. Africanos en bares en Nairobi. Y fueron estos mismos africanos los que empecé a conocer en mis propios viajes por el continente. Queríamos hablar de literatura africana, política, política económica.
But almost invariably, every single time, we would end up discussing Twitter. And that's when I realized what this was. We were standing in the middle of something amazing, because for the first time ever young Africans could discuss the future of our continent in real time, without the restriction of borders, finances and watchful governments. Because the little known truth is many Africans know a lot less about other African countries than some Westerners might know about Africa as a whole. This is by accident, but sometimes, it's by design. For example, in apartheid South Africa, black South Africans were constantly being bombarded with this message that any country ruled by black people was destined for failure. And this was done to convince them that they were much better off under crushing white rule than they were living in a black and free nation. Add to that Africa's colonial, archaic education system, which has been unthinkingly carried over from the 1920s -- and at the age of 15, I could name all the various causes of the wars that had happened in Europe in the past 200 years, but I couldn't name the president of my neighboring country. And to me, this doesn't make any sense because whether we like it or not, the fates of African people are deeply intertwined. When disaster hits, when turmoil hits, we share the consequences. When Burundians flee political turmoil, they go to us, to other African countries. Africa has six of the world's largest refugee centers. What was once a Burundian problem
Sin embargo, casi invariablemente en cada ocasión, acabábamos discutiendo Twitter. Y fue cuando me di cuenta de qué se trataba. Estábamos parados en medio de algo sorprendente, porque por primera vez en la historia los jóvenes africanos podían discutir el futuro del continente en tiempo real, sin la restricción de las fronteras, las finanzas y gobiernos vigilantes. Por lo poco conocida que es la verdad muchos africanos saben mucho menos sobre otros países africanos que algunos occidentales saben sobre África en su conjunto. Esto es por accidente, pero a veces, es por diseño. Por ejemplo, en el apartheid de Sudáfrica, los sudafricanos negros fueron bombardeados constantemente con el mensaje de que cualquier país gobernado por personas de raza negra estaba destinado al fracaso. Y esto se hizo para convencerlos de que eran mucho mejor bajo el aplastante dominio blanco de lo que estaban viviendo en una nación negra y libre. Añadan al sistema colonial africano, el arcaico sistema de educación que se ha arrastrado sin pensarlo desde la década de 1920... a los 15 años, podía nombrar todas las diversas causas de las guerras que habían sucedido en Europa en los últimos 200 años, pero no podía nombrar al presidente de mi país vecino. Y para mí, esto no tiene ningún sentido porque nos guste o no, los destinos de la gente de África están profundamente entrelazados. Cuando ocurre un desastre, cuando la inestabilidad golpea, compartimos las consecuencias. Cuando huyen de Burundi por la agitación política, vienen a nosotros, a otros países africanos. África tiene seis de los centros de refugiados más grandes del mundo. Lo que antes era un problema de Burundi
becomes an African problem. So to me, there are no Sudanese problems or South African problems or Kenyan problems, only African problems because eventually, we share the turmoil. So if we share the problems, why aren't we doing a better job of sharing the successes? How can we do that? Well, in the long term, we can shoot towards increasing inter-African trade, removing borders and putting pressure on leaders to fulfill regional agreements they've already signed. But I think that the biggest way for Africa to share its successes is to foster something I like to call social Pan-Africanism. Now, political Pan-Africanism already exists, so I'm not inventing anything totally new here. But political Pan-Africanism is usually the African unity of the political elite. And who does that benefit? Well, African leaders, almost exclusively. No, what I'm talking about is the Pan-Africanism of the ordinary African. Young Africans like me, we are bursting with creative energy, with innovative ideas. But with bad governance and shaky institutions, all of this potential could go to waste. On a continent where more than a handful of leaders have been in power longer than the majority of the populations has been alive, we are in desperate need of something new, something that works.
se convierte en un problema africano. Así que para mí, no hay problemas sudaneses o problemas sudafricanos o problemas kenianos, solo hay problemas africanos porque, al final, compartimos la agitación. Y si compartimos los problemas, ¿por qué no vamos a hacerlo mejor compartiendo los éxitos? ¿Cómo podemos hacer eso? En el largo plazo, podemos aumentar el comercio interafricano, eliminar fronteras y presionar a los líderes para que cumplan los acuerdos regionales que ya han firmado. Pero creo que la forma más grande de África de compartir sus éxitos es fomentar algo que me gusta llamar panafricanismo social. Ahora, la política panafricanista ya existe, así que no estoy inventando nada nuevo aquí. Pero política panafricanismo es por lo general la unidad africana de la élite política. ¿Y quiénes se benefician? Bien, los líderes africanos, casi exclusivamente. No, de lo que estoy hablando es del panafricanismo del africano común. Jóvenes africanos como yo, llenos de energía creativa, con ideas innovadoras. Sin embargo, con las malas y temblorosas instituciones de gobierno, todo este potencial se podría perder. En un continente donde poco más de un puñado de líderes han estado en el poder más que la mayoría de las poblaciones que han vivido, tenemos la necesidad desesperada de algo nuevo, algo que funcione.
And I think that thing is social Pan-Africanism. My dream is that young Africans stop allowing borders and circumstance to suffocate our innovation. My dream is that when a young African comes up with something brilliant, they don't say, "Well, this wouldn't work in my country," and then give up. My dream is that young Africans begin to realize that the entire continent is our canvas, is our home. Using the Internet, we can begin to think collaboratively, we can begin to innovate together. In Africa, we say, "If you want to go fast, you go alone, but if you want to go far, you go together." And I believe that social Pan-Africanism is how we can go far together. And this is already happening. Access to these online networks has given young Africans something we've always had to violently take: a voice. We now have a platform. Before now, if you wanted to hear from the youth in Africa, you waited for the 65-year-old minister of youth -- (Laughter) to wake up in the morning, take his heartburn medication and then tell you the plans he has for your generation in 20 years time. Before now, if you wanted to be heard by your possibly tyrannical government, you were pushed to protest, suffer the consequences and have your fingers crossed that some Western paper somewhere might make someone care. But now we have opportunities to back each other up in ways we never could before. We support South African students who are marching against ridiculously high tertiary fees. We support Zimbabwean women who are marching to parliament. We support Angolan journalists who are being illegally detained. For the first time ever, African pain and African aspiration has the ability to be witnessed by those who can empathize with it the most: other Africans. I believe that with a social Pan-Africanist thinking and using the Internet as a tool, we can begin to rescue each other, and ultimately, to rescue ourselves. Thank you. (Applause)
Y creo que eso es el panafricanismo social. Mi sueño es que los jóvenes africanos dejen de permitir que las fronteras y las circunstancias sofoquen la innovación. Mi sueño es que cuando un joven africano venga con algo brillante, no le digan: "Bueno, esto no funcionaría en mi país", y luego se rindan. Mi sueño es que los jóvenes africanos empiecen a darse cuenta de que todo el continente es nuestro lienzo, es nuestro hogar. Con Internet, podemos empezar a pensar de forma colaborativa, podemos empezar a innovar juntos. En África, se dice: "Si quieres ir rápido, ve solo, pero si quieres llegar lejos, ve acompañado". Y creo que el panafricanismo social es como podemos ir muy lejos juntos. Y esto ya está sucediendo. El acceso a estas redes en línea ha dado a los jóvenes africanos algo que siempre hemos tenido que tomar con violencia: una voz. Ahora tenemos una plataforma. Antes, si uno quería saber de los jóvenes en África, esperaba a que el ministro de la juventud, de 65 años de edad, (Risas) se despertara en la mañana, tomara su medicación para la gastritis y después les dijera los planes que tenía para su generación dentro de 20 años. Antes, si querías ser escuchados por su posiblemente tiránico gobierno, eran empujados a protestar, sufrir las consecuencias y tener los dedos cruzados para que un medio occidental les pusiera atención. Pero ahora tenemos la oportunidad de respaldarnos el uno al otro en formas en las que nunca antes se pudo. Apoyamos a los estudiantes de Sudáfrica que protestan contra las ridículamente altas tarifas terciarias. Apoyamos a las mujeres de Zimbabwe que están marchando al parlamento. Apoyamos a los periodistas angoleños que son detenidos ilegalmente. Por primera vez, el dolor de África y la aspiración de África tiene la capacidad de ser vistos por aquellos que pueden identificarse más con ellas: otros africanos. Creo que con un pensamiento panafricanista social y usando Internet como una herramienta, podemos empezar a rescatar a unos de otros, y en última instancia, rescatarnos a nosotros mismos. Gracias. (Aplausos)